<page>
    <title>AccessibleComputing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10</id>
    <redirect title="Computer accessibility" />
    <revision>
        <id>854851586</id>
        <parentid>834079434</parentid>
        <timestamp>2018-08-14T06:47:24Z</timestamp>
        <contributor>
        <username>Godsy</username>
        <id>23257138</id>
        </contributor>
        <comment>remove from category for seeking instructions on rcats</comment>
        <model>wikitext</model>
        <format>text/x-wiki</format>
        <text bytes="94" xml:space="preserve">#REDIRECT [[Computer accessibility]]

            == Etymology, terminology and definition ==
{{main|Definition of anarchism and libertarianism}}
{{see also|Glossary of anarchism}}
The etymological origin of ''anarchism'' is from the Ancient Greek ''anarkhia'', meaning &quot;without a ruler&quot;, composed of the prefix ''an-'' (i.e. &quot;without&quot;) and the word ''arkhos'' (i.e. &quot;leader&quot; or &quot;ruler&quot;). The suffix ''[[-ism]]'' denotes the ideological current that favours [[anarchy]].{{sfnm|1a1=Bates|1y=2017|1p=128|2a1=Long|2y=2013|2p=217}} ''Anarchism'' appears in English from 1642{{sfn|Merriam-Webster|2019|loc=&quot;Anarchism&quot;}} as ''anarchisme'' and ''anarchy'' from 1539.{{sfn|''Oxford English Dictionary''|2005|loc=&quot;Anarchism&quot;}} Various factions within the [[French Revolution]] labelled their opponents as ''anarchists'', although few such accused shared many views with later anarchists. Many revolutionaries of the 19th century such as [[William Godwin]] (1756–1836) and [[Wilhelm Weitling]] (1808–1871) would contribute to the anarchist doctrines of the next generation, but they did not use ''anarchist'' or ''anarchism'' in describing themselves or their beliefs.{{sfn|Joll|1964|pp=27–37}}

The first political philosopher to call himself an ''anarchist'' ({{lang-fr|anarchiste}}) was [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]] (1809–1865), marking the formal birth of anarchism in the mid-19th century. Since the 1890s and beginning in France,{{sfn|Nettlau|1996|p=162}} ''[[libertarianism]]'' has often been used as a synonym for anarchism{{sfn|Guérin|1970|loc=&quot;The Basic Ideas of Anarchism&quot;}} and its use as a synonym is still common outside the United States.{{sfnm|1a1=Ward|1y=2004|1p=62|2a1=Goodway|2y=2006|2p=4|3a1=Skirda|3y=2002|3p=183|4a1=Fernández|4y=2009|4p=9}} On the other hand, some use ''libertarianism'' to refer to [[individualistic]] [[free-market]] philosophy only, referring to [[free-market anarchism]] as ''libertarian anarchism''.{{sfn|Morris|2002|p=61}}

While the term ''libertarian'' has been largely synonymous with anarchism,{{sfnm|1a1=Marshall|1y=1992|1p=641|2a1=Cohn|2y=2009|2p=6}} its meaning has more recently diluted with wider adoption from ideologically disparate groups,{{sfn|Marshall|1992|p=641}} including both the [[New Left]] and [[libertarian Marxists]] (who do not associate with [[authoritarian socialists]] or a [[vanguard party]]) as well as extreme [[Liberalism|liberals]] (primarily concerned with [[civil liberties]]).{{sfn|Marshall|1992|p=641}} Additionally, some anarchists use ''[[libertarian socialist]]''{{sfnm|1a1=Marshall|1y=1992|1p=641|2a1=Chomsky|2y=2005|2p=123|3a1=Cohn|3y=2009|3p=6|4a1=Adams|4a2=Levy|4y=2018|4p=104}} to avoid anarchism's negative connotations and emphasise its connections with [[socialism]].{{sfn|Marshall|1992|p=641}} Matthew S. Adams and [[Carl Levy (political scientist)|Carl Levy]] write that ''anarchism'' is used to &quot;describe the [[anti-authoritarian]] wing of the [[socialist movement]]&quot;.{{sfn|Adams|Levy|2018|p=104}} Similarly, [[Noam Chomsky]] describes anarchism, alongside libertarian Marxism, as &quot;the libertarian wing of socialism&quot;.{{sfn|Chomsky|2005|p=123}} [[Daniel Guérin]] wrote:
&lt;blockquote&gt;[A]narchism is really a synonym for socialism. The anarchist is primarily a socialist whose aim is to abolish the exploitation of man by man. Anarchism is only one of the streams of socialist thought, that stream whose main components are concern for liberty and haste to abolish the State.{{sfn|Guérin|1970|p=12}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

While [[opposition to the state]] is central to anarchist thought, defining anarchism is not an easy task as there is a lot of discussion among scholars and anarchists on the matter and various currents perceive anarchism slightly differently.{{sfn|Long|2013|p=217}} Hence, it might be true to say that anarchism is a cluster of political philosophies opposing [[authority]] and [[hierarchical organisation]] (including [[Anarchism and capitalism|capitalism]], [[Anarchism and nationalism|nationalism]], the [[State (polity)|state]]  and all associated [[institution]]s) in the conduct of all [[human relations]] in favour of a society based on [[decentralisation]], [[freedom]] and [[voluntary association]]. However, this definition has the same shortcomings as the definition based on anti-authoritarianism (which is an ''[[a posteriori]]'' conclusion), anti-statism (anarchism is much more than that){{sfnm|1a1=McLaughlin|1y=2007|1p=166|2a1=Jun|2y=2009|2p=507|3a1=Franks|3y=2013|3pp=386–388}} and etymology (which is simply a negation of a ruler).{{sfnm|1a1=McLaughlin|1y=2007|1pp=25–29|2a1=Long|2y=2013|2pp=217}} Nonetheless, major elements of the definition of anarchism include the will for a non-coercive society, the rejection of the state apparatus, the belief that human nature allows humans to exist in or progress toward such a non-coercive society and a suggestion on how to act to pursue the ideal of anarchy.{{sfn|McLaughlin|2007|pp=25–26}}

[[Herbert L. Osgood]] claimed that anarchism is &quot;the extreme antithesis&quot; of [[authoritarian communism]] and [[state socialism]].{{sfn|Osgood|1889|p=1}} [[Peter Marshall (author)|Peter Marshall]] states that &quot;[i]n general anarchism is closer to socialism than liberalism. [...] Anarchism finds itself largely in the socialist camp, but it also has outriders in liberalism. It cannot be reduced to socialism, and is best seen as a separate and distinctive doctrine&quot;.{{sfn|Marshall|1992|p=641}} According to [[Jeremy Jennings]], &quot;[i]t is hard not to conclude that these ideas&quot;, referring to [[anarcho-capitalism]], &quot;are described as anarchist only on the basis of a misunderstanding of what anarchism is&quot;. Jennings adds that &quot;anarchism does not stand for the untrammelled freedom of the individual (as the 'anarcho-capitalists' appear to believe) but, as we have already seen, for the extension of individuality and community&quot;.{{sfn|Jennings|1999|p=147}} [[Nicolas Walter]] wrote that &quot;anarchism does derive from liberalism and socialism both historically and ideologically. [...] In a sense, anarchists always remain liberals and socialists, and whenever they reject what is good in either they betray anarchism itself. [...] We are liberals but more so, and socialists but more so&quot;.{{sfn|Walter|2002|p=44}} Michael Newman includes anarchism as one of many [[socialist traditions]], especially the more socialist-aligned tradition following Proudhon and [[Mikhail Bakunin]].{{sfn|Newman|2005|p=15}} [[Brian Morris (anthropologist)|Brian Morriss]] argues that it is &quot;conceptually and historically misleading&quot; to &quot;create a dichotomy between socialism and anarchism&quot;.{{sfn|Morriss|2015|p=64}}

== History ==
{{main|History of anarchism}}

=== Pre-modern era ===
[[File:Paolo Monti - Servizio fotografico (Napoli, 1969) - BEIC 6353768.jpg|thumb|upright=.7|[[Zeno of Citium]] (c. 334 – c. 262 BC), whose ''[[Republic (Zeno)|Republic]]'' inspired [[Peter Kropotkin]]{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=70}}]]
During the prehistoric era of mankind, an established authority did not exist. It was after the creation of towns and cities that institutions of authority were established and anarchistic ideas espoused as a reaction.{{sfn|Graham|2005|pp=xi–xiv}} Most notable precursors to anarchism in the ancient world were in China and Greece. In China, [[philosophical anarchism]] (i.e. the discussion on the legitimacy of the state) was delineated by [[Taoist]] philosophers [[Zhuang Zhou]] and [[Laozi]].{{sfnm|1a1=Coutinho|1y=2016|2a1=Marshall|2y=1993|2p=54}}

Anarchic attitudes were also articulated by tragedians and philosophers in Greece. [[Aeschylus]] and [[Sophocles]] used the myth of [[Antigone]] to illustrate the conflict between rules set by the state and personal [[autonomy]]. [[Socrates]] questioned Athenian authorities constantly and insisted on the right of individual freedom of conscience. [[Cynicism (philosophy)|Cynics]] dismissed human law (''[[Nomos (sociology)|nomos]]'') and associated authorities while trying to live according to nature (''[[physis]]''). [[Stoics]] were supportive of a society based on unofficial and friendly relations among its citizens without the presence of a state.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=4, 66–73}}

During the [[Middle Ages]], there was no anarchistic activity except some ascetic religious movements in the [[Muslim world]] or in Christian Europe. This kind of tradition later gave birth to [[religious anarchism]]. In the [[Sasanian Empire]], [[Mazdak]] called for an [[egalitarian]] society and the [[abolition of monarchy]], only to be soon executed by Emperor [[Kavad I]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=86}}

In [[Basra]], religious sects preached against the state. In Europe, various sects developed anti-state and libertarian tendencies. Libertarian ideas further emerged during the [[Renaissance]] with the spread of [[humanism]], [[rationalism]] and [[reason]]ing through Europe. Novelists fictionalised ideal societies that were based on voluntarism rather than coercion. The [[Age of Enlightenment]] further pushed towards anarchism with the optimism for social progress.{{sfn|Adams|2014|pp=33–63}}

=== Modern era ===
During the [[French Revolution]], partisan groups such as the [[Enragés]] and the {{lang|fr|[[sans-culottes]]}} saw a turning point in the fermentation of anti-state and federalist sentiments.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=4}} The first anarchist currents developed throughout the 18th century as [[William Godwin]] espoused [[philosophical anarchism]] in England, morally delegitimising the state, [[Max Stirner]]'s thinking paved the way to [[Individualist anarchism|individualism]] and [[Pierre-Joseph Proudhon]]'s theory of [[Mutualism (economic theory)|mutualism]] found fertile soil in France.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=4–5}} By the late 1870s, various anarchist schools of thought had become well-defined and a wave of then unprecedented [[globalization]] occurred from 1880 to 1914.{{sfn|Levy|2011|pp=10–15}} This era of [[classical anarchism]] lasted until the end of the [[Spanish Civil War]] and is considered the golden age of anarchism.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=4–5}}

[[File:Bakunin.png|thumb|upright|Mikhail Bakunin, who opposed the Marxist aim of [[dictatorship of the proletariat]] and allied himself with the federalists in the First International before his expulsion by the Marxists]]
Drawing from mutualism, [[Mikhail Bakunin]] founded [[collectivist anarchism]] and entered the [[International Workingmen's Association]], a class worker union later known as the First International that formed in 1864 to unite diverse revolutionary currents. The International became a significant political force, with [[Karl Marx]] being a leading figure and a member of its General Council. Bakunin's faction (the [[Jura Federation]]) and Proudhon's followers (the mutualists) opposed [[state socialism]], advocating political [[abstentionism]] and small property holdings.{{sfnm|1a1=Dodson|1y=2002|1p=312|2a1=Thomas|2y=1985|2p=187|3a1=Chaliand|3a2=Blin|3y=2007|3p=116}} After bitter disputes, the Bakuninists were expelled from the International by the [[Marxists]] at the [[1872 Hague Congress]].{{sfnm|1a1=Graham|1y=2019|1pp=334–336|2a1=Marshall|2y=1993|2p=24}} Anarchists were treated similarly in the [[Second International]], being ultimately expelled in 1896.{{sfn|Levy|2011|p=12}} Bakunin famously predicted that if revolutionaries gained power by Marx's terms, they would end up the new tyrants of workers. In response to their expulsion from the First International, anarchists formed the [[St. Imier International]]. Under the influence of [[Peter Kropotkin]], a Russian philosopher and scientist, [[anarcho-communism]] overlapped with collectivism.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=5}} Anarcho-communists, who drew inspiration from the 1871 [[Paris Commune]], advocated for free federation and for the distribution of goods according to one's needs.{{sfn|Graham|2005|p=xii}}

At the turn of the century, anarchism had spread all over the world.{{sfn|Moya|2015|p=327}} It was a notable feature of the international syndicalism movement.{{Sfn|Levy|2011|p=16}} In China, small groups of students imported the humanistic pro-science version of anarcho-communism.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=519–521}} Tokyo was a hotspot for rebellious youth from countries of the far east, travelling to the Japanese capital to study.{{sfnm|1a1=Dirlik|1y=1991|1p=133|2a1=Ramnath|2y=2019|2pp=681–682}} In Latin America, [[Anarchism in Argentina|Argentina]] was a stronghold for [[anarcho-syndicalism]], where it became the most prominent left-wing ideology.{{sfnm|1a1=Levy|1y=2011|1p=23|2a1=Laursen|2y=2019|2p=157|3a1=Marshall|3y=1993|3pp=504–508}} During this time, a minority of anarchists adopted tactics of revolutionary [[political violence]]. This strategy became known as [[propaganda of the deed]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=633–636}} The dismemberment of the French socialist movement into many groups and the execution and exile of many [[Communards]] to penal colonies following the suppression of the Paris Commune favoured individualist political expression and acts.{{sfn|Anderson|2004}} Even though many anarchists distanced themselves from these terrorist acts, infamy came upon the movement.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=633–636}} [[Illegalism]] was another strategy which some anarchists adopted during this period.{{sfn|Bantman|2019|p=374}}

[[File:Makhno group.jpg|thumb|left|Nestor Makhno with members of the anarchist [[Revolutionary Insurrectionary Army of Ukraine]]]]
Despite concerns, anarchists enthusiastically participated in the [[Russian Revolution]] in opposition to the [[White movement]]. However, they met harsh suppression after the [[Bolshevik government]] was stabilized. Several anarchists from Petrograd and Moscow fled to Ukraine,{{sfn|Avrich|2006|p=204}} notably leading to the [[Kronstadt rebellion]] and [[Nestor Makhno]]'s struggle in the [[Free Territory]]. With the anarchists being crushed in Russia, two new antithetical currents emerged, namely [[platformism]] and [[synthesis anarchism]]. The former sought to create a coherent group that would push for revolution while the latter were against anything that would resemble a political party. Seeing the victories of the [[Bolsheviks]] in the [[October Revolution]] and the resulting [[Russian Civil War]], many workers and activists turned to [[communist parties]] which grew at the expense of anarchism and other socialist movements. In France and the United States, members of major syndicalist movements such as the [[General Confederation of Labour (France)|General Confederation of Labour]] and the [[Industrial Workers of the World]] left their organisations and joined the [[Communist International]].{{sfn|Nomad|1966|p=88}}

In the Spanish Civil War of 1936, anarchists and syndicalists ([[Confederación Nacional del Trabajo|CNT]] and [[Federación Anarquista Ibérica|FAI]]) once again allied themselves with various currents of leftists. A long tradition of [[Spanish anarchism]] led to anarchists playing a pivotal role in the war. In response to the army rebellion, an anarchist-inspired movement of peasants and workers, supported by armed militias, took control of Barcelona and of large areas of rural Spain, where they [[collectivised]] the land.{{sfn|Bolloten|1984|p=1107}} The [[Soviet Union]] provided some limited assistance at the beginning of the war, but the result was a bitter fight among communists and anarchists at a series of events named [[May Days]] as [[Joseph Stalin]] tried to seize control of the [[Republican faction (Spanish Civil War)|Republicans]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=xi, 466}}

=== Post-war era ===
[[File:Rojava Sewing Cooperative.jpg|thumb|Rojava's support efforts for workers to form cooperatives is exemplified in this sewing cooperative]]
At the end of [[World War II]], the anarchist movement was severely weakened.{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=xi}} However, the 1960s witnessed a revival of anarchism, likely caused by a perceived failure of [[Marxism–Leninism]] and tensions built by the [[Cold War]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|p=539}} During this time, anarchism took root in other movements critical towards both capitalism and the state such as the [[Anti-nuclear movement|anti-nuclear]], [[Environmental movement|environmental]] and [[peace movement]]s, the [[counterculture of the 1960s]] and the [[New Left]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=xi, 539}} It also saw a transition from its previous revolutionary nature to provocative [[anti-capitalist reform]]ism.{{sfn|Levy|2011|pp=5|p=}} Anarchism became associated with [[punk subculture]] as exemplified by bands such as [[Crass]] and the [[Sex Pistols]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=493–494}} The established [[feminist]] tendencies of [[anarcha-feminism]] returned with vigour during the [[second wave of feminism]].{{sfn|Marshall|1993|pp=556–557}} [[Black anarchism]] began to take form at this time and influenced anarchism's move from a [[Eurocentric]] demographic.{{sfn|Williams|2015|p=680}}

    {{R from move}}
    {{R from CamelCase}}
    {{R unprintworthy}}</text>
        <sha1>42l0cvblwtb4nnupxm6wo000d27t6kf</sha1>
    </revision>
</page>